hi again in the spirit of adding and
broadening perspective which is what
rule Omega is all about I thought it
might be nice to do a follow-up to the
last video I did which was about rule
Omega and myself and three people from a
group to get together reasonably
regularly to practice our rule Omega
skills if you like I had a conversation
about rule Omega itself and so I thought
it might be fun for you to watch that so
without any further ado here it is I
hope you enjoy it
rendering unto signal what is signal so
up regulating and rendering into noise
what is noise so down regulating
basically means you know assuming that
that the person that you're talking to
is intelligent and they have information
that you don't and searching for that
and seeking to understand it and some
amplifier
I suppose while also understanding that
whenever you're dealing with something
that is a new unknown topic that there's
going to be a lot of you know searching
around finding ways of expressing things
that may not be may not be easy and the
result of that is going to end up being
a fair bit of noise you know so or
static so which makes it difficult to
hear the signal so that when you're
listening to someone else you're trying
to ignore and suppress that to some
extent and bring the you know the bit of
truth that's there and amplify it to the
point that that everyone else can hear
it and that you can continue working on
I was like sort of building up this you
know increasing view of clarity and
truth
I suppose that was
really good intro for a really good
definition of the Omega I think one
thing that shown now brought up I think
in a previous conversation was the fact
that in a conversation noise can also be
coming from the listener as they're
listening they can be the listener can
be bringing their own you know their own
[Music]
misunderstandings their own lenses of
trauma that they might be viewing the
situation through and so exactly as you
described it's it comes down to both
both looking for the signal
understanding that the distortion of
signal may not entirely be coming from
the other person may not be coming from
the other person at all it may be it may
be coming from you and and maybe you you
have a you know maybe you define a word
wrong and the other person actually
makes complete sense maybe neither of
you are defining a word wrong maybe
you're just defining the word
differently but because of that
difference of definition there's a
complete dissonance between the two of
you when in fact the underlying signal
is actually the same and your meaning is
the same
so yeah that's just I guess getting a
little bit more specific but I I I think
I've pretty fully back up everything you
said Kylee yeah I think both of those
are very important I liked your
definition kind of like Chad on Heather
that um I got is what I thought signal
was was in listener like into what the
speaker is saying but it's like up to
the listener to kind of separate to be
like what is here that is real and what
am I making it mean right like what is
like when something happens an event
happens we don't react to the event we
react to our story about the events
right so someone's late and we make it
mean that they're disrespectful and they
don't care about us and they know we
don't know why they're actually late
it's the reactions
ass right - fine wait why were you late
instead of having that whole cascade and
that yeah that is like fine this signal
is in like the communication between
because both as the speaker isn't
anywhere near as eloquent as I used to
be and how I wish I was I know there's a
lot of noise in my signal and yet I know
the signal is really important and
finding that in other people as well
like when someone says something that I
am naturally curious about I'm a much
better conversationalist than when I
have to fake it right when I have to
like oh how is the weather today how are
you doing how is like I can't even fake
that curiosity that piece of it
I think one thing that's interesting too
is it almost becomes more important
I shouldn't say more important but maybe
more relevant the farther you get away
from face-to-face communication because
there's more and more opportunity for it
to break down so for example in facebook
comments or on a tweet really easy to be
misconstrued and yet people very quickly
tend to assume they know what someone
means when in fact they may be
completely misinterpreting that person's
words so it's it's interesting it it it
it it it applies differently in in
asynchronous communication because you
have to really slow down and you can't
just react you have to question you have
to you have to kind of ask for specifics
and then the person has to reply so it
can it can be quite slow but in the end
what is revealed and just like Eric you
talked about in your video you get the
cylinder instead of the circle fighting
with the square right over who's right
yes it takes more time it takes patience
it takes discernment and you have to be
willing to be wrong and so with that in
case you are wrong which you very well
may be but at the end if you can reveal
a cylinder it's so rewarding and it's
it's it's so much more constructive and
it then allows us to go on and have the
next step in whatever conversation might
be unfolding and maybe reveal another
cylinder and it also helps us to III I'm
going to phrase this in a way that could
be displeasing but I hope I put it right
it also encourages us to seek out
disagreement in dispute because you know
in that in that example I gave in the
video of the cylinder if there if there
is no argument between the two of them
then there's no possibility for that
revelation oh my god it's a
three-dimensional shape not a
two-dimensional shape without the
argument
both of them just walk past oh yeah it's
a rectangle oh yeah it's a circle with
do you know what I mean they the
argument is itself the the the the thing
with generally without the argument
there is no possibility of the learning
so you know I I think yes I actually
like that analogy on a lot of levels
it's ease disagreement as an opportunity
exactly yeah
yep well which you know which it
certainly is you also think about you
know in a similar sort of vein like
diversity versus sameness gentleman if
everyone is coming from the same
perspective and seeing something as just
a square or everyone is seeing something
as just a circle then you never get us
full of picture as you do if you've got
you know someone kind of going okay from
this angle it looks like it's you know
this weird kind of shape like that you
know which it could if you were just
seeing it as a shadow someone else is
seeing it is the square someone else is
seeing it is the you know as the circle
and you kind of put them all together
and you get that kind of picture but in
order to do that you've not only have to
have well actually maybe even an
argument isn't necessary you just need
to have the different perspectives and
allow them to to be expressed and heard
and considered hope for me will you ever
talk about that and the disagreement is
that yes the spark is also the UM like
the community piece of it like if you're
the only one who sees a square and
everybody else sees a circle that is a
hard position to be in same with it like
everyone's gonna argue that your truth
is it your truth when it's only like it
says it any less true it's still like it
was 50/50 it's the same rightness as if
it was 90 you know 10 but if you have no
one else backing you up it's it's um
like just the dynamic of a group it's
very different if you're 5050 or if
you're like the 1% 99% dynamic code of
discernment finding the noise in the
signal right like we let that definitely
permeate that culture is what we go off
of right like if you think the moon
landing is a hoax you're ridiculous even
if you've never looked into the moon
landing right like cuz that's just our
natural what we say in society and so if
you haven't looked into it that's gonna
be your your your go-to that's
interesting there so the the there's the
false positive as well right in the
signal there's the reading something a
signal which isn't actually
signal yeah it comes across to you as
signal but it isn't actually signal
again it's your noise turning noise into
signals and turning noise into precede
signal right which is why I think what
Heather was saying before the idea of
speaking back you know what I mean
speaking back to people checking re
saying what they've said clarifying
words that have been used that can that
can hold multiple definitions is a
really really important part of not
ending up in apparent conflict when as
you said really your your signal is
actually in alignment but because of a
word you're using that you see
differently it feels like they're out
I've noticed so many times that apparent
arguments actually come down to a
definition of a single word but people
using differently the conversation that
I had with my husband yesterday around
around a discussion that's come up
through the course of the year in one of
his groups about professional courage
and it's that's it's that willingness to
leave what what the the group norm or
the group understanding is and to
actually express that you know that that
different perspective and when we were
talking about it I said you know hey I
wonder if when anyone's talking about
that whether they think about sort of
like the first follower or like the
second person that's essentially coming
in and applying rule Omega in their you
know they're listening for that that
dissenting opinion or that that
different many thing ends and up
regulating it enough so that the rest of
the the rest of the group or the cool we
can actually hear it as well because
like one lone person as I was very
difficult to be in that position as as
Jubilee said but there's also that other
other role or other thing that can be
done which is the first person to apply
rule of maegor in that setting
completely changes the nature of that
that dissenting view point so that then
it's available for the up for the whole
group to listen to interesting things of
you talk about like naming what is being
said in the group and minds you've liked
the circling dynamic and the feeling of
vulnerability of saying like la Heather
I think you said this in a logical sense
I have no problem doing that like in a
oh what you said is there was a cylinder
and there's a circle and a square got
that but if it's like the actual I don't
know like being like you look like
you're frustrated that piece of it is
really hard for me I don't know like to
come into like I would rather be the
person that sees the square when
everyone else sees the circle then um
name that everyone sees the circle and I
see the square like I don't know there's
something Valle nura Belen thank
goodness we have diversity that other
people it's probably the opposite
there's also there's something sort of
different from that but that I want to
put out here which is that just because
you apply rule Omega and the other
person applies with Omega doesn't mean
you're going to agree you could still
have 99 percent disagreement but if
you're both coming in good faith and
applying rule Omega you will find the
one percent of residents and be able to
build something on to that but it
doesn't necessarily mean that we're all
in agreement we just aren't
communicating well we can still
fundamentally disagree and apply rule
Omega but we can do it in a way that
brings us closer to truth instead of
makes us fight and destroy each other
one of these the very first conversation
we had where Eric and I were talking
about or we were talking about Hana and
ended up finding that that you used
honor the way that I use integrity and
I'm not sure about vice versa but um but
that was a really interesting example of
that it's like that was our signal was
that you know that you know we both sort
of thinking about the same concept but
in a way the noise was the words
themselves anyway we've got right but
it's but it's
from perfect we only have to use it
carefully especially when talking about
difficult things things that you talked
about before you got to be that's
exactly what you said Kyle I mean you
summed it up so perfectly it's exactly
that you've got to try and upregulate
your own signal as best you can
given that you've never really talked
about this stuff before and it's going
to be clumsy and you as the listener try
not regulate my signal as well right
IIIi like that I don't conceive it in
quite those terms the up regulation and
down regulation but it's actually it's
actually I'm finding it a more and more
useful way of looking at it what was
coming if we are having a conversation
whether there's multiple of us or one of
us we could bring our own selves to the
table and we have our own perspective
and that's rule Omega right that we're
like trying to find the signal in the
noise but starting from a somewhat blank
state not that the people or blank
slates state um is that like creating an
organization creating a product for
creating anything from the ground up
when we're looking for what is the 1% we
agree on and what can we build from
there what is the 10% whatever the
percentages that we agree with because I
feel that is a big sticking point for
game be moving forward it's like
everyone has their individual projects
their own individual there's nothing
wrong with that but if we can't also
start something from the ground up can
also be already being like what is I
don't there's something different
between the group and like where we're
starting on different sides we're trying
to find the commonality versus finding
the commonality and then building from
there um there's something that's like
that's kind of the game I want to play
it's like building it from the ground up
it's like what is the culture what are
the rules / no rules right like I'll
make a rule is I think submission and
then building it from that point it's
like what is the
thing we want to create what is the
process we want to use what is like and
finding building it from the ground up
that's all I wanted to go Sparky
I feel like yeah there's maybe something
I don't know if this applies there but
something about how even when people are
fundamentally coming from different
points of view and they disagree to to a
little a large extent and there's very
little common signal if they're using
the principles of rule Omega they can
still come together around that small
percentage of signal that they share and
work together because the wave wave rule
Omega works it's almost like the noise
then just becomes like we accept the
noise we accept that that's part of the
equation and it's okay for it to be
there and then that allows us to work
with people who have vastly different
opinions from our own on things that we
feel very strongly about because at the
end of the day if we can work with
people like that and they can work with
us then we can avoid a lot of conflict
so yeah I don't know if that that he
strikes a chord with anything you were
saying or not something that came up for
me while Jubilee was talking was
something that came up in a conversation
I had with Roland us awhile ago he's
really into nonviolent communication and
he is of the opinion and I have to say
it makes a great deal of sense to me
he's of the opinion that almost all
conflicts can be resolved if you can
successfully separate needs from
strategies that almost all conflicts are
over strategies right how to accomplish
a given need but actually when you come
right down to it the needs that we both
have here are very clear and can be
agreed upon right without without really
any dispute at all it's how you go about
meeting those needs that is the dispute
and so if you can start from that point
of I acknowledge your needs you
acknowledge my needs
we both accept that it just it just it
just starts the space from which you can
maybe build strategies that aren't in
conflict with each other
yeah which is maybe also a great a great
point around the fact that rule Omega is
one tool and there are many many tools
in this area and the more that we can be
aware of them and apply them the easier
this whole process becomes think about
the relationship there between and
signal it's like a radio channel or
radio frequency that we're all probably
pretty good and quicker to get tuning
into because it's something that we we
all sort of have in common it's kind of
like it's almost like a language you
know I mean estate we have like shared
vocabulary then it's much easier to you
know it's much easier do things like
achieve coherence it's much easier to
pick out the signal and I'm thinking
with something like like needs as well
because there's hope you know or at
least some of them are so common to all
of us it also probably makes it easier
to pick out pick out that signal so if
we focus on that and then kind of build
around with rather than starting with
the concept that nobody knows I'm trying
to build up a signal based on that is
probably difficult whereas if you're
starting with something that you can
acknowledge easily and then build out
from there yeah that might just it might
be easier anyone just occurred to me
when I was listening to you there during
nonviolent communication yeah so you
explained the concepts start at the
starting point of the explanation of the
concept is identifying the needs that it
is purporting to meet right that's what
grounds it in in something of substance
yeah it's a real thing because it's
meeting a need which we can all identify
with because these needs are as you say
largely universal right
how much of either
have you heard about non-violent
communication how much do you know about
it only a very small bit in theory so
it's it's it's kind of it's applying
principles from you know I suppose that
a sort of dotted throughout like
everything I've ever learned about
psychology if that makes sense it's just
making at a particular particular focus
on it so I guess I have been very lazy
and not felt the need to take too much
into that particular that particular
framework I think one could become a
much more skilled skilled is the wrong
word I'm not quite sure what the right
word is for rule Omega practitioner if I
can use I'm not quite sure what the
right word would be to describe anyway I
think MVC could really inform the
process of rulinea I think is a great
deal to learn just in terms of how to
conceptualize the dynamics of you know
how
conflicts arises through the failure to
recognize a need or the confusion of
strategy with need I just think that's I
think it's a really really really useful
lens with which to see it through I
really like nonviolent communication the
first time I was introduced to it was
through there's an hour-long talk by the
person who invented it I can never
remember his name Marshall something
rather or something Marshall and it's a
good talk I don't know if anyone's
posted around the game be its face
before but it's part of the to get into
the transition which is just a website
about transitioning to resource-based
economy and she has her own anyway she
has a set of things you have to do to
move through the levels and one of the
first things is to watch the night
nonviolent communication it's one of the
longer videos because it's an hour long
but I've watched it a couple times in
it's pretty powerful but I wanted to
mention mckylie have said that like we
all like something or it's easily
accessible because we all have the same
basic needs um I don't feel that at all
because I don't access them easily
I don't accept my own emotions or my own
needs so I'm like have the surface level
I have to go in it's like when I watched
that I'm like I need to print off a
document put it on my mirror that is
like here are the human needs so when
I'm I'm feeling emotionally triggered or
something's happening that I can look at
it and be like oh yeah that one actually
is born so I think there's a lot of
things because we are good at them and
it comes so easily to us we assume that
this must be a like common we don't have
any like we all like needs are so
universal like there's days I forgot to
eat or drink water like that level of
not realizing in my own basic meet so
for debt if I need is connection and I'm
trying to meet it you know through some
ridiculous format okay and I think I'm
more self-aware because I know that
about myself and I've been seeking out
how to figure that out then a lot of
people who are in the same boat they
don't like that's not a good assumption
that we make it that's broad that
everyone has that I'm especially maybe
in the game B's face because we're
intellectual a lot even though we're
also doing the Leichhardt face piece of
it and
that diversity doesn't mean to like them
let's not let's ignore everyone's needs
like we need people like you who that is
easy for to maybe help the rest of us
who it's less easy for I don't know what
that looks like but I'd like yeah I'm
going to do a lot of regulation down
regulation there so um
Jubilee I hear you absolutely on the
specifics that we may not know what our
own needs actually are like the specific
ones and we may not recognize someone
else's specific needs either so what I
was actually thinking about more was the
the more meta thing of that humans have
needs mm-hmm I mean and that they that
they exist that and that that's
something that we can relate to so it's
basically it's kind of it's the
grounding and the that sort of that core
thing of going yes
you know we do actually all need to eat
we do actually all need to sleep you
know it's kind of that thing you know
even if you're not good at it in the
moment or in a you know in a
specifically you know like you might
forget to eat or someone else might
forget to sleep or something like that
it's like it's still maybe that's bad
strategies right that's bad strategies
that's nothing to do with the needs
that's executing bad strategies to meet
the needs you know it's again really
important to keep these things separate
from each other you not eating when you
were hungry that's bad strategizing not
that's nothing to do with the need that
make sense actually I wanted to ask you
Eric she'll expand on that what you said
confusion of strategy with needs so this
would be a good point oh god alright I
me think if I can come up with an
example real quick all right so let's
say that okay so yeah the there's a
river and there's two towns either side
of the river and you know the fact that
there's a river between them is a
problem and so they all get together and
they decide that they need a bridge
right to connect the two towns and they
argue about what kind of bridge is going
to be blah blah blah blah blah so the
argument is being sent around a strategy
because the bridge is a strategy the
need is to connect the two towns
strategy to do so is the bridge but why
they're arguing that what kind of bridge
to built they haven't even considered
the possibility of a tunnel for example
or an airport or a heliport or a ferry
or whatever you know what I mean so this
is what I mean about getting confused
between strategies and needs now if you
keep the need clear at the outset you
know the bridge has become the need but
actually not it's not the need the
bridge is the strategy the need is to
connect the Townsend so if you kept the
need clear all the way through and the
possibility for other other strategies
to meet that need could emerge this is
the difficulty of getting confused
between strategies and needs the need
becomes sorry the strategy becomes
confused with the need right and so
you're meeting the strategy you don't
meeting the need you're meeting the
strategy that's really clear thank you
this actually brings to mind something
else that might be relevant here which
is from a Buddhist perspective looking
at being able to separate sort of who's
who someone is in in how they present to
the world or their I want to say surface
but but their their self and who someone
is sort of at a at a deeper essential
level beneath that and being able to
recognize that that those are separate
things and that we all we all we all
bring something that is the same that
has needs to any conversation and that
all all the stuff we stack on top of
that that's different in all of us is
just that it's just stacked on top like
the strategy it's and when we conflate
the two just like with needs and
strategies that's when we run into
trouble because then we think that all
these surface things that we see are the
person when in fact that that's not what
they are at all it's interesting
came up when you starts like what
appearance was was signal the noise and
that as well right when you meet someone
in their like tattoos and they have a
certain and you put or you know certain
race gender anything where you're gonna
have bias and stuff that's put on them
and to find that like the truth the
signal that is who they are is almost
even more important than the signal in
the conversation right like my humanity
sees the humanity in you whether you're
you know looks like you come off of an
Amish place or you look like you you
know our sex worker it doesn't matter
there's like humanity there there's the
essence and the needs that are mmm
that's so interesting
only on that signal and noise thing as
well so one of the other things that
I've done in terms of like getting
myself trained in various things is it's
an image consultant and that's one of
the things that we sort of think about a
lot as well as is congruence between
what is sort of what is the essence of a
person and then the way that they
present because as much as we don't want
to we do all you not quickly start to
form judgments of people not necessarily
is it good or bad but in what we can
what we feel that we can expect from
them so we used stereotypes and it that
was actually a huge learning for me
because um I'd like to generally think
that I don't do that with people like I
don't judge them based on how they look
and we did this exercise there was a
there was a bunch of us and we had
different photos and we had to just you
know write down our thoughts about you
know what how old is this person how
many kids do they have what kind of car
do they drive what's their job and so on
and so forth so you know it's so we all
wrote these things down as best we could
and then you know I from completely
different cultures results that we got
were almost exactly the same though we
were all making exactly the same
judgments based on just a photo of
somebody so but yes that's that same
kind of thing it's like you can
intentionally or unintentionally create
noise in your appearance so you know so
someone who
you know I put some tattoos or you know
does the pink hair or the you know any
of those kinds of things it's like very
expressing something and then it then
you have to work out underneath that
like what is the you know what is it
that they're actually trying to express
what is the you know what's the true
signal and what's what's noise again and
I get something yeah is that noise is
almost like the lack of congruence and
that you know in that first instance
it's you know and it doesn't doesn't
compute you know when it's not what you
expect then yeah and I was like the say
because I a very consciously spent a lot
of my life trying to conform and feeling
like I never quite got there like I
didn't know how to fit in at work or
school or that kind of thing once I gave
it up once I'm like in a giant onesie
I'm like a banal I can wear what I want
to where I want to where it's
comfortable I put off a different thing
right like I'm like I'm always that's
okay I'm good with that I don't you know
you have to get to know me to know who I
am I'm not gonna like necessarily
presence on the outside although a giant
elephant onesie is funny how it is but
like because I don't know like I want an
authentic world I want people to dress
and be who they are whether that is real
or not signal or noise but this like it
was like the Trump thing I talked to her
earlier it's like when people over us
it's like a wear a suit or no one's
gonna take you seriously it's like but
we've collectively decided that and we
can see the people in suits aren't
really more respectable so like at what
point do we let go of that bias maybe
never maybe I do just have to open that
I need to be more more business but I
don't want to
and then like sexism and everything else
comes into it like men can be
billionaires in our t-shirt and jeans
and women are expected to you know like
care about fashion and I just never
never have but anyway I'm gonna stay
with that for like the signal I want the
signal from my noise and communication I
want that to get better whereas I kinda
just want my appearance to get more and
more and more and more noisy for like my
own internal signal right of like this
is what I want to wear because I want to
wear it not
because it puts on a certain thing and
other people that is their true essence
as well like they're like yes and I want
to look good cool awesome go as
fashionistas you want just not expecting
it from from like everyone else so in a
way there would be zero noise in your
appearance from you but there might be
noise in other people reacting yeah
interesting that's something that's
entirely unavoidable right I mean
whether it's blue hair and tattoos or
whether it's an elephant onesie or
whether it's a suit a tie you know we
are going to and it'll be different for
different people I I hear what you said
before Carly but nevertheless there is
going to be some variation but I mean
for example Jubilee associate suits with
you know being shady and corrupt you
know what I mean at least as much those
people that don't wear suits so you know
they will have different associations
but I don't think there's ever I mean
it's a lovely thought not to judge
people on their appearances right but I
but I think it's a forlorn thought I
think the best we can do is know that
we're doing it and not pay not pay too
much attention to those judgements and
not put any stock in them I think that's
the best we can do I don't think we can
prevent making them I'm just gonna
mention there's three minutes left and
I'm not gonna jump on the next call cuz
I have to do Christmas stuff I was
already there's clicking kids room all
that good stuff yeah I just sorry I'm
just going to shove something in
hopefully before you leave jibley just
to sort of pull together everything that
we were talking about there it's like
what is noise and what is signal is
highly dependent on context hmm so some
of it's the listener but some of its
going to be the group some of its going
to be you know the cultural expectations
and so on so you know within within the
banking world not wearing the suit would
be very very noisy but within like an
artist's world wearing a suit would be
very very noisy unless it was a really
cool and trendy suit that would be
different
she one of my friends is its Muslim and
she moved in with me she wore the hijab
and while she was in Vancouver she ended
up not wearing it and I thought her like
faith was kind of slipping away and she
was like no the point of a head job is
to fit in is to like have people not
look at your appearance and here that is
done better with oh one oh it's like
it's just oh how weird is that like it's
more about the essence of like actual
the rule is to keep your head covered
right it's like well isn't that a
beautiful different isn't that a
beautiful little sort of micro analogy
of game a versus game B right yeah the
game a would would require you to wear a
hijab because that's the rule
whereas game B requires you not to wear
a hijab because a hijab is about not
being seen it's about following the
spirit and not the and not the letter I
like I like that I like that that's a
really really nice little don't know
what you call it but there's a very nice
one